Finding Aid for Division of Research Development and Administration (University of Michigan) Records, 1919-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Division of Research Development and Administration (University of Michigan) records 1919-1996
University of Michigan. Division of Research Development and Administration.
42.5 linear feet
87156 Bimu C141 2
The records of the Division of Research Development and Administration (1919-1996) encompass the DRDA and all of its predecessor organizations, including the Department of Engineering Research, the Engineering Research Institute, the University of Michigan Research Institute, and the Office of Research Administration. Record types include correspondence, topical subject files, research grant files, meeting minutes, financial records, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material has been received from DRDA or its predecessor agencies in several accessions beginning in 1953 (Donor no. 4462 ). The series of PRISM weekly reports was received in 2004.
The Division of Research Development and Administration records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Division of Research Development and Administration record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 31-32
Mortimer E. Cooley became the dean of the Department of Engineering in 1904 with the firm conviction that privately-sponsored research should be integrated into the College's activities. This idea was popular with neither the faculty nor private industry, and it was not until World War I that the College, through the efforts of Clifford D. Holley, acting chairman of the Department of Chemical and Metallurgical Engineering, interested the Michigan Manufacturers' Association in sponsoring research. Largely on the strength of this activity, the regents in 1919 created the new Department of Engineering Research within the College of Engineering. The department's purpose was to foster privately sponsored research. Its emphasis was on basic research, rather than routine testing and analysis.
The new department's growth was slow. Some faculty members continued to resist the department's work. Private industry proved reluctant to fund projects. Corporations were particularly concerned about a lack of patent protection for discoveries made at the university. Some work was forthcoming, however, and in 1928 a patent trust agreement was approved by the Regents, making it possible for a sponsor of research to reserve any patent rights that a project might generate.
World War II and the postwar environment fundamentally changed the nature of sponsored research and its source of funding. Prior to the war sponsored research had been almost exclusively engineering projects. During and immediately after the war, sponsored research in the physical sciences grew dramatically. Equally significant was the change in the source of funds and their increase. In 1940 the department received two dollars in private money for every one dollar in public funds. Total sponsored research then amounted to about $158,000. In the academic year 1945 sponsored research had grown to over one million dollars. Three-quarters of that sum came from public funds.
Recognizing both the broadening of sponsored research as well as the tremendous increase in funding, the Regents in 1948 reconstituted the Department of Engineering Research outside of the College of Engineering as the Engineering Research Institute (ERI). The ERI was given responsibility for fostering and overseeing non-University funded research activities in the fields of engineering and the physical sciences. As a part of this responsibility the Aeronautical Research Center, located at Willow Run Airport, was placed under the ERI's jurisdiction in 1949.
Sponsored research continued to grow at the University at phenomenal rates. By the academic year 1951 it had reached two million dollars per year. The areas of sponsored research also continued to grow. The Medical School, in particular, began to receive large grants of funds for specific projects. To cope with this continued growth in the breadth and volume of sponsored research, the Regents, in 1958, reorganized the ERI, renaming it the University of Michigan Research Institute (UMRI). While UMRI was empowered to foster as well as oversee research throughout the University, in practice the organization exercised only administrative oversight tasks. It did not choose to sponsor any projects, and operational control of projects reporting to the ERI was transferred to the various teaching departments or to the Willow Run Laboratories. The vacuum created by the decision of the UMRI not to undertake the fostering of research was also filled by the creation of the Institute of Science and Technology.
In 1959 UMRI's focus was shifted by the creation of the position of Vice President for Research. While created independently of the vice-president, UMRI quickly became the administrative office through which the Vice President for Research worked. In 1961 this de facto arrangement was formalized with the reorganization of UMRI as the Office of Research Administration (ORA). ORA served formally as the administrative arm of the Vice President for Research and bore primary responsibility for relieving sponsored project's technical staff from involvement with non-technical, procedural matters. ORA's jurisdiction covered the entire University. It employed, in 1962, over one hundred individuals.
At its formation ORA, reflecting the office's long history, was primarily research oriented. Throughout the 1960s, however, the office's mission broadened to include sponsored grants in non-research areas such as teaching. This slow but constant broadening of authority led to one more reorganization of the office in 1973. At that time, it became the Division of Research Development and Administration, retaining all of the functions given to the ORA at its creation in 1961, as well as formally adding to the office the responsibilities that it had accrued during the 1960s.
The records of the Division of Research Development and Administration (1919-1996) encompass both the DRDA and all of its predecessor organizations. The papers have been divided into seven major series: Governing and Oversight Bodies (1919-1964), Staff and Committee Records (ca. 1922-1979), Administrative Files (1922-1972), Correspondence Files (1943-1972), Willow Run Laboratories (1946-1966), Directors' Files, and several boxes of Research Grant Files on microfilm. There are also four smaller series: the Engineering College Research Council (1959-1961), Review of the DRDA - Report to Harold Shapiro, 1980, Engineering Research Institute - miscellaneous research reports, Photographs, and Programmed Research Information System at Michigan (PRISM) Reports.
Subjects:
Engineering.; Engineering College Research Council.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Division of Research Development and Administration.; University of Michigan. Engineering Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Great Lakes Research Division.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; University of Michigan. Office of Research Administration.; University of Michigan--Research.; University of Michigan Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Research.; Burroughs, Robert Eli, 1904-1978.; Sawyer, Ralph A. (Ralph Alanson), 1895-1978.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Computers.; Engineering.; Laboratories.; Medicine--Michigan.; Negatives.; Photographs.; Radar.; Rockets.; Synchrotrons.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Division of Research Development and Administration.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Research.; North Campus (University of Michigan)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Governing and Oversight Bodies 1919-1964
  Included in the Governing and Oversight Bodies series is material from the Regents (1919-1945), minutes of the organization's executive body (1920-1964) and files of the Vice President for Research (1957-1964). The Regent's material consists of excerpts from the official proceedings regarding research at the university, and communications sent to the regents by DRDA and its predecessors. The minutes of the executive body (which has various names under DRDA's predecessors) represents an apparently complete set of records from 1920 until 1964. The files of the Vice President for Research are those of Ralph A. Sawyer, first individual to hold that office. They are arranged alphabetically and are particularly interesting for information about the Great Lakes Research Institute (1956-1963) and the Institute of Science and Technology (1957-1964). There is also information about funding for the Aerospace Building, obtained through the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, and a proposed missile range on Michigan's Keweenaw peninsula.
  - Regents Proceedings (excerpts) 1919-1959 (Box 1)
  - Regents Communications 1925-1945 (Box 1)
  - Minutes and Related Documents of the Executive Committee 1920-1938, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    (Executive Committee Log)
  - Minutes and Related Documents of the Administrative Committee 1936-1948
    - 1936-1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - Minutes and Related Documents of the Engineering Research Council 1949-1964
    - Indexed Minutes 1949-1956 (Box 2)
    - Membership Lists 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Vice-President for Research (Ralph A. Sawyer) 1956-1964
    - Atmospheric Research (meteorology) 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Bio-Medical Data Processing Research Center Proposal 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Cardiovascular Center (NIH site visit, Tecumseh Project) 1961 (Box 2)
    - Commission on Government Operations in Research and Development 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - Conductron Corporation 1961-1964 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    - Cyclotron, Request to Congress for Federal Funding 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Department of Defense (Disallowances) 1963 (Box 2)
    - Economic Development 1963 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Compensation 1959-1963 (Box 3)
    - Funding (Grants versus Contracts) 1964 (Box 3)
    - Governor’s Science Advisory Board 1959-1962 (Box 3)
    - Great Lakes Research Institute 1956-1963, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Infrared Astrophysical Observatory and Tracking Station, Hawaii (ARPA Project) 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - Institute of Science and Technology
      - Establishment of 1957-1959 (Box 3)
      - Executive Committee 1960-1964 (Box 3)
      - Military Research Policy 1960 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1959-1964 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1960-1964, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - President’s Report 1964 (Box 3)
      - Regents’ Briefing December 1960 (Box 3)
      - Reorganization 1960 (Box 3)
      - Search for a Director 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Keweenaw (Michigan) Missile Range Proposal 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project 1960-1964, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - National Aeronautics and Space Administration 1962-1964 (Box 4)
      (Funding for Space Research Building)
    - Office of Research Administration, Establishment 1961-1964 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Research Institute 1957-1961 (Box 4)
    - Water Pollution Laboratory 1961-1964 (Box 4)
- Staff and Committee Records circa 1922-1979
  Staff and Committee Records have been divided into four subseries: minutes, administrative file, financial records, and newspaper clippings. Minutes of staff meetings are complete from 1948 to 1964. The administrative file (1948-1979) is largely that of Dennis Cebulski. It deals primarily with various problems encountered by the Office of Research Administration (ORA) and DRDA in their efforts to rationalize the administration of grant funds at the university. The office also served as a data-collecting agency, and so a number of completed questionnaires are found in this file. Financial records consist of two types of documents, project ledgers and various statements of overall research. The project ledgers detail expenses for specific research projects and are arranged by account number. They date from ca. 1922 to 1948. Balance sheets, monthly statements and trial balance make up most of the remainder of the financial records and date from 1940 to 1950. Newspaper clippings include a very few items from 1927 and a group of items beginning in 1941 and ending in 1955.
  - Minutes 1948-1979
    - 1948-1979 (Box 4)
  - Administrative File 1948-1979
    - Alumni Development Data Base Project 1973 (Box 4)
    - American Council on Education Survey 1971 (Box 4)
    - Awards, Faculty Research 1967 (Box 4)
    - Biology of Ageing 1979 (Box 4)
    - Bureau of the Budget 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - Cancer Research 1972 (Box 4)
    - Carnegie Study 1961 (Box 4)
    - College Resource Analysis System 1971 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Titles, Perquisites and Policies Relating to Research Appointees 1961 (Box 4)
    - Data Analysis, no date (Box 4)
    - Data Processing Service 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Energy Research 1973 (Box 4)
    - Engineering Research Council 1952-1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Engineering Research Council 1948-1957 (Box 5)
    - Expenditure Transfers 1976 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Communication 1975 (Box 5)
    - Government Procurement, Commission on 1971 (Box 5)
    - Graduate School Data Request 1973 (Box 5)
    - Indirect Costs Data 1961-1963 (Box 5)
    - Information Systems Inventory 1975 (Box 5)
    - Institute of Science and Technology -- College of Engineering Proposal 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    - Libraries, Funding 1977 (Box 5)
    - Location of Research Projects 1970 (Box 5)
    - Management Information System 1969-1976, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Reports 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Organization within University 1961-1971 (Box 5)
    - Orientation Program for Project Directors 1963 (Box 5)
    - Overhead Negotiations 1961 (Box 5)
    - Overhead Provisional Rate 1962 (Box 5)
    - Personnel Forms (proposed) circa 1975 (Box 5)
    - Personnel, Research Participants 1962-1964 (Box 5)
    - Postdoctorals 1966 (Box 5)
    - Postdoctoral Interview 1971 (Box 5)
    - Procedures for Processing Proposals, Grants, etc. 1960 (Box 5)
    - Professional Scientific Salaries Survey 1962 (Box 5)
    - Program Budget Evaluation System 1972 (Box 5)
    - Proposal Reports 1971 (Box 5)
    - Proposal Study: Success of Individual University Units in Obtaining Grants 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    - Research Administration lectures 1962 (Box 5)
    - Research Policies 1972 (Box 6)
    - Research Units 1973 (Box 6)
    - Space Research, no date (Box 6)
    - Special Bulletins 1953-1959, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Sponsored Research and Expendable Restricted Funds Comparison 1960 (Box 6)
    - Summer Appointments 1966 (Box 6)
    - Supervisor’s Manual circa 1956 (Box 6)
    - Volume of Research
      - Graphs 1962-1972 (Box 6)
      - 1963-1973 (Box 6)
  - Financial Records circa 1922-1948
    - Closed Project Ledgers circa 1922-1947
      - Accounts 1-500 (Box 6)
        (Ledger 1)
      - Accounts 500-800 (Box 7)
        (Ledger 2)
      - Accounts 800-M208 (Box 7)
        (Ledger 3)
      - Accounts M209-M674 (Box 8)
        (Ledger 4)
      - Miscellaneous Accounts (Box 8)
        (Ledger 5)
      - 1946-1947 (2 ledgers) (Box 9)
    - Open Project Ledgers circa 1927-1948
      - Accounts 490-M402 (Box 9)
      - Accounts M438A-M809 (Box 10)
    - Annual Reports 1946-1947 (Box 10)
    - Balance Sheets July 1946-July 1950 (Box 10)
    - Monthly Statements July 1946-June 1949 (Box 10)
    - Trial Balances July 1940-June 1947 (Box 10)
    - Trust Fund and Fellowship Account July 31, 1927-September 30, 1948 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Gas Associated Equipment Purchase (Box 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1927, 1941-1955 (Box 11)
- Engineering College Research Council 1956-1961
  The Engineering College Research Council was a national organization of engineering colleges engaged in research activities. The papers represent the involvement of Robert E. Burroughs, longtime director of the Engineering Research Institute (ERI), University of Michigan Research Institute (UMRI), and ORA, in this organization.
  - Executive Committee 1960-1961 (Box 11)
  - Committee on Relations with Industrial Agencies 1959-1960 (Box 11)
  - General
    - 1956-1959 (Box 11)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 11)
    - 1961 (Box 11)
- Review of the DRDA
  - Report to Harold Shapiro 1980 (Box 11)
- Engineering Research Institute
  - Miscellaneous research reports (Box 12)
- Photographs
  The Photographs (located in boxes 12, 13, and 20) fall into three subseries: prints of images used or considered for publication in the Annual Report or Research News or its predecessors ERI News and UMRI News); negatives produced by the DRDA Photographic Services; and photographs from the Administrative Files (1922-1972). For the first two subseries, the prints are arranged by the year in which they were used. To find prints related to a particular subject, the researcher should look at the publications in the Bentley Library printed collection, then go to the folder for the year in which photos of the desired subject were used. Negatives of many of these photos are found in the Photographic Services negative files, which are arranged by subject. Some miscellaneous prints are also arranged by subject. The Administrative File photographs are mostly taken from in-house reports, although there are some miscellaneous images at the end of the series. The photographs in this last series are arranged by subject. The photographs include images of researchers, research equipment, and research projects, especially engineering and medical research at the University of Michigan; photos of campus scenes and buildings, especially related to the early development of North Campus; also a few color negatives of Michigan travel scenes.
  - Photos used in Publications
    - Photos used in Annual Report, 1951-1962
    - Photos used in Research in Engineering and the Physical Sciences, 1951 (Box 12)
    - Photos used in Research News and its predecessors
      - 1951-1973 (Box 12)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous topics
      - Buildings
        - Central Campus and other (Box 13)
        - North Campus (Box 13)
      - Computing Center 1976 (Box 13)
      - Mobile Automotive Laboratory (Box 13)
      - Phoenix Memorial Laboratory (Box 13)
      - Portraits (Box 13)
      - Ships (Box 13)
      - Space Research Laboratory dedication (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Photos produced by DRDA Photographic Services 1948-1976, negatives with copy prints attached
    - African art (Box 13)
    - Architecture (Box 13)
    - Bible (Box 13)
    - Bioengineering (Box 13)
    - Biophysics (Box 13)
    - Botanical Gardens (Box 13)
    - Buildings
      - Central Campus (Box 13)
      - North Campus (Box 13)
    - Carillon (Box 13)
    - Chemical and metallurgical engineering (Box 13)
    - Civil engineering (Box 13)
    - Coal technology (Box 13)
    - Computing Center (Box 13)
    - Cyclotron (Box 13)
    - Dental research (Box 13)
    - Dental School (Box 13)
    - Engineering mechanics (Box 13)
    - Gerontology (Box 13)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute (Box 13)
    - History of Art (Box 13)
    - Institute of Fisheries (Box 13)
    - Institute of Science and Technology (Box 13)
    - Marine engineering (Box 13)
    - Mathematics (Box 13)
    - Medical
      - Arthritis (Box 13)
      - Burn research (Box 13)
      - Histochemistry (Box 13)
      - Holden Perinatal (Box 13)
      - Internal medicine (Box 13)
      - Medical, Miscellaneous (Box 13)
      - Nursing (Box 13)
      - Nutrition (Box 13)
      - Obstetrics (Box 13)
      - Office of Educational Resources and Research (Box 13)
      - Psoriasis (Box 13)
      - Special pictures (Box 13)
      - Surgery (Box 13)
      - University Health Information Service (Box 13)
    - Museums (Box 13)
    - Pharmacy (Box 13)
    - Phoenix Project (Box 13)
    - Slavic (Box 13)
    - Stearns Collection (Box 13)
    - Underwater biology (Box 13)
    - Travel (Box 13)
      (color negatives of Mackinac Island, Tahquamenon Falls, and Pictured Rocks)
    - Video (Box 13)
    - White-tail deer (Box 13)
    - Whiting, Allen (Box 13)
    - Women's issue (Box 13)
  - Administrative Photographs
    - Various Buildings, Laboratories, and Equipment at UM circa 1920s (Box 20)
    - Daylighting Laboratory circa 1950s (Box 20)
    - Rocket Propulsion Laboratory-Report Photographs 1954 (Box 20)
    - Mortimer E. Cooley Foundation for Fundamental Research (includes both report and photographs) 1929 (Box 20)
    - Aerial Views (Box 20)
    - Interior Views (Box 20)
    - People (Box 20)
- Administrative Files 1922-1972
  The Administrative Files series covers the fifty-year period from 1922 to 1972, although the majority of the material falls into the fifteen years between 1950 and 1965. The records are basically a subject file, arranged alphabetically, except for the first three folders which give some history on the DRDA and its predecessors. The "Annual Reports" offer fairly complete coverage of the main office from the 1920s to the mid-1960s. There are also reports from smaller departments within the DRDA, such as the Cooley Electronics Laboratory and the Office of Business Manager for Sponsored Research. Another major series is that of "Committees," which is a catch-all heading for any group called such. All the committee records were brought together here. Other major series include "Buildings," "Laboratories," and "Research," which includes major projects run by the DRDA.
  - History of DRDA 1911-1921, 1932, 1948, 1953, 1968, 3 folders (Box 14)
    (Original documents and written histories)
  - Aircraft-Use of 1958 (Box 14)
  - Annual Reports (1922-1972)
    - Reports 1922/23-1966/67, 10 folders (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1952-1967, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Distribution Lists 1952-1954 (Box 14)
    - Cooley Electronics Laboratory Reports 1962-1966, 1968/69 (Box 14)
    - Editorial Office Reports 1962/63-1971/72 (Box 14)
    - Office of Business Manager for Sponsored Research Reports 1959/60-1966/67 (Box 14)
    - Program Development Group Reports 1970/71-1971/72 (Box 14)
  - "Big Lie" (Box 14)
  - Buildings
    - General 1957-1963 (Box 14)
    - Cooley Building-General 1952-1968, 3 folders
      - Maintenance 1957-1959 (Box 14)
      - Plans 1952 (Box 14)
      - Space Utilization 1957-1971 (Box 14)
    - Engineering Research Laboratory (Geophilus and Valet, Architects Report) 1956 (Box 14)
    - North Campus 1955-1957
      - "First Phase" Report 1955 (Box 14)
      - Summary File 1955-1956 (Box 14)
    - Research Administration Building 1961-1963 (Box 15)
    - Space 1957 (Box 15)
    - Space, no date (Box 15)
    - 912 N. Main 1956, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Business Manager File "X" 1954-1957 (Box 15)
  - Committees
    - General 1955-1958 (Box 15)
    - Advisory 1956-1958 (Box 15)
    - Budget Advisory 1953-1956 (Box 15)
    - Buffer 1955 (Box 15)
    - Computers 1957-1959 (Box 15)
    - Dynamics 1956-1958 (Box 15)
    - ERI Building Program 1950-1954
      - Meeting Minutes 1951-1952 (Box 15)
    - Engineering Research Laboratory Meeting Minutes 1955-1958 (Box 15)
    - Fluids Laboratory Meeting Minutes 1954-1955 (Box 15)
    - Management for Fluids Research 1955-1958 (Box 15)
    - Meteorology 1957-1958 (Box 15)
    - "Removal Costs" (Relocation of New Faculty) 1955-1957 (Box 15)